this is a mangy mini kya 38 the greater
discourse on the destruction of Craney
I only go through a bit of it yes funny
you choose there so this is the setting
beginning of the suitor so on one
occasion a pernicious view or
unbeneficial view hmm because opposite
is from kalyana view right it's not like
it's evil like himself
it's a harmful so now I'm that occasion
are harmful to you had arisen in a
bhikkhu named sati son of a fisherman
thus as I understand the Dumber taught
by the blessed one it is in this same
consciousness that runs it is the same
consciousness that runs and wanders
through the round of rebirths not
another well it is the same
consciousness that runs and wanders too
samsara not another consciousness and
several because other because again
people might just too easily dismiss
that of course that's the wrong view but
you want to ask yourself do you really
know why it is wrong here and now not
just because the Buddha said so but do
you see for yourself why he said it is
wrong view well that we already require
somebody to start clarifying the
designation consciousness or Vignon oh
whatever you want to call it and people
I realize that very often end up using
these words without any clarity in
regard to what they actually mean or
what what are you designating when you
say consciousness to yourself not to
others just simply you say basic
consciousness consciousness what is
consciousness what are you what are you referring to
what are you what are you referring to
where is that questioning what do you
want to know so that's how you begin
this process of clarification so to
speak but the point is once you start
asserting the end clearly that something
the big was something who was you know
people might assume reading the suti is
like an idiot imagine a buddha called
him an idiot but for different reasons
he he even are the Shiva is a simpleton
but no he clearly understood what
consciousness is and then he thought
it's that thing that he understood that
sort of stays for the future lives and
so on and the problem with that the
reason whatever view is wrong is because
any notion of this life in the future
life and if there is a connection
between the two as in this is what gets
reborn or simply asking a question what
gets reborn the Lord it assumes that
something gets reborn any of those
attitudes require an external point of
view to your experience right here right
now and then in itself it's active odda
so he's he's thinking so because he has
a wrong view now even after his own
experience from that he then assumed
further that it is this consciousness
that moves around it goes to the next
life and next life so what he said just
revealed his wrong view right here right
now because of which because of that
assumption amount of our assumption of
the external self did not just he's not
undoing he's clearly adding more to it
with all these other views that he's
developing like all this is the rebirth
and this is that and the Buddha said
this because of all of that he's
actually harming himself but you cannot
your only reference point is the
experience you have this life that's it
so when you think about before or after
this life it's within this experience as
a whole so you then assuming that is
this life and in the next life as the
valid next life perception of it it's
all within this experience right here
right now so the whole thing can not
well he certainly cannot be proven in a
sense you cannot see it the way you
think you're seeing it which is that
external manner from which you can step
aside and then see yourself here and
then yes when this bit goes this is the other
yes when this bit goes this is the other
part that moves to the next life and to
the next life nobody can see things that
had not even the Buddha himself
so assuming such a view is entirely
entirely mistaken from the point of view
of the nature of things
no and well if he's what if he someone
says or if he says that it's the same
consciousness that is in every
experience that I experienced yesterday
the same constant again as it is today
again that statement would be rooted in the
that statement would be rooted in the
assumption of the external point of view
in regard to the consciousness and
consciousness it some of the
interpretation when they say like the
moments of consciousness that lasts a
certain number of milliseconds or
whatever no like that's inconceivable
not just that you can't measure other
people's consciousness but you can
actually see your own so when people try
to say no no and you're somehow not the
time stands still and then you can see
you can't
as the Buddha described what is present
in Samadhi
it's basically nama Rupa vijnana
vijnanam group it's the parkings its
present in Samadhi so whether it's some
other not somebody the your experiences
there is a whole the Fargate says but
you think in a somatic you do some super
special power of stopping the time and
stepping outside of the five ugly
incidents witnessing it with your eyes
that you think there's a fantasy because
the Buddhists notice that he said it in
Samadhi it's again he's just absence of
lost aversion delusion he said there is
still contact there is still attention
that he's still feeling that is -
mindfulness in that one by one
not even I care about sorry Buddha's
attempt
but then you also said even when people
remember previous lives of future life
they remember one of the aggregates
right here right now one of the
aggregates or all of them within that
you can't step outside in the same sense
your yesterday is a new tomorrow are
within your today your previous life
your future life are also within you
today so new projecting this linear view
of this cosmology basically of your
rebirth and what moves it's completely
gratuitous and utterly divorced from any
kind of like reflexive recognition and
discernment it's just what you can
recognize in discerner it's completely
wrong so if somebody says all my
consciousness now only again this you
external point of view just on a smaller
scale it's all about next slide it's
about next moment but still they're
trying to disassociate themselves from
from their experiences the whole film to
see did they're entirely enclosed within
it as if you're trapped in a coffin
buried in the ground
you can't concede the way out so even
I'm just saying it's the same
consciousness that hears you it sees you
sure joke right now yeah yeah that can
only be assumed and saying oh you can
say it's a different consciousness or
you can say it's both same and different
you can mystified and then you can
mystify your mystification and say well
it's neither the same no different
consciousness either way each of those four statements
either way each of those four statements
designates your assumption of external
point of view to the consciousness
that's what we said no I didn't say it
is the same I didn't say it isn't the
same I didn't say it's neither same
they're not the same so I need a saying
it's both same and all the same no
neither the same they're not the same I
didn't say any of it because saying any
of it still feed you of you designate
you assumption yeah
because consciousness consciousness
literally means presence of things so
you can't even think you can't even
think about the pure presence and
whatnot that's after the meaningless and
as mystical as as as it sounds so what
is present how you discern presence on
account of things that are present on
account phenomena that have arisen so
that's the conscious aspect of there is
an experience so you must define that
presence as some sort of energy well
it's clearly a thought in your mind
which means that thought is present
which means that thought cannot be that
presence which consciousness is that
just how it works the fact that you
imagined it means you're conscious of it
you can't be conscious of your
consciousness and what's it saying it's
saying it's wisdom is to be developed
consciousness we understood yeah I
understood exactly you can't cuz they
were required to step outside yeah
exactly that's that's a good point you can
that's that's a good point you can
discern it you can understand it by
doing so you develop wisdom by
understanding the consciousness you
understand the nature of present the
nature of around the natural
manifestation and yeah and where you are
well exactly well yes to that yeah there
won't be much left to you if you
understand things correctly in that
sense as in you maintain your sense of
self through that external assumption to
your own experience that's just how it
works not abandoned and yeah it's very
it's as subtle as that it's not like -
that goes by boy it's not like boo to
you that goes around saying oh I think I
am this or I invent no it's just a
subtle assumption that you can see
yourself in the external manner for
example order you can see what's in for
you or you can see the next day in
amended it's independent of you
assumption of a public world assumption
of a public space and time that we are
in not that it's in our experience and
so on all those things
go back to that subtle subtle fact
enough antibody assumption with external
point of view one way or the other
subtle assumption of the externality
so I'll continue to miss Kayla the
subtle assumption of an external view
either go after your own experience
himself that is why he why he's wrong
that's why it's a wrong view exactly so
several bhikkhus having heard about this
bhikkhus sati whens him and asked him
friend sati is it true that's such a
unhelpful harmful view how harmful view
has arisen on you know so he says
exactly exactly so friends as I
understand the Talmud taught by the
Blessed One it is the same consciousness
that runs and wanders through the round
of rebirths not another then those big
who is designed to detach him from that
harmful view president questioned cross
question him said thus friend sati do
not say sir do not misrepresent the best
one is not good to misrepresent the best
one the best one would not speak thus
for in many ways the Blessed One has
stated consciousness to be dependently
arisen as I said since there was no
presence without something being present
since without a condition there is no
origination of consciousness well but
that translation though origination
could imply the time as in no the first
thing comes then the consciousness is a
second but that's not the case is the
Buddha said consciousness and things
that you are conscious of as in nama
Rupa the old are like two sticks
simultaneously chopping each other up
you remove one the other one cannot
remain standing and that's not a
momentary thing that you can observe
because if you think you're observing
calm a nama Rupa dependence means you're
a nama Rupa dependence means you're
assuming you left outside of it so in
this particular case even in the
broadest terms you can't have presence
unless there's something present so when
you think the world letters presents in
your mind that is present for you
thoughts are present in your imagination
abstraction if this present means you're
conscious of it that's how you can know
things at any given time because they
are present but people sort of with
attach presence so it would detach
presence from course things and then
when they think about the presence the
pure presence the presence of the
presence the presence of your awareness
there all of these things it's it's they
fail to see that that also isn't a
reason thing that is present for them
and thus cannot stand for that presence
of that very thing and he clearly
assumes that that presence is
independent and it moves around for the
next life and next life so the Buddha
said did they they said to him didn't do
good as say that the conscious cannot
stand on its own
so don't it's not a question is the same
conscience so different the point is
consciousness of any kind is
inconceivable without something to be
conscious of simultaneously and you
can't step outside of it to see it
because you are it that's when in the
mirror said in one in one of his letters
maybe he said if you attend to nama Rupa
well your experience is undermined by
the independence of banana if you try to
attend to the presence the nature of
Inanna your experience is undermined by
the presence of independence of nama
Rupa as in you can't take two things to
the same extent at the same time for me
because they require you to step outside
of them but you can't because you are
them that's not talking about the
peripheral of the Sun in the background
or wherever you're attending whatever
it's present anyhow
anyhow
you know pure consciousness yeah exactly
that's a complete fallacy and your pure
consciousness you could like that's a
concept yeah
that's an idea that is present as such
and people are obviously not conscious
of it because they think that what
consciousness is because when you say
presence of presence one of those
presences is not presence it's the
object of the other presence by you
trying to level them on the same ground
means not understanding either there is
an assumption and you maintain
assumption or because you're actively
choosing to hold onto it you're
maintaining it by not undoing it
by not fully understanding it that's all
it takes to maintain ignorance not make
the effort to understand the ignorance
because people think attachments and
assumptions and so on is something you
do and then all you have to do is stop
doing it and then you're free from it oh
I'm attached to my possessions I will
throw away my possessions that's I'm
free from attachment no I'd assume the
external point of view okay so then I'll
just sort of stop assuming it you can't
just stop assuming it the only way to
stop assuming this third of you is to
understand the mistake of external view
they're incompatible incompatibility
they the discrepancy the impulsive
including receivable aspect of it you
understand that it truly external point
of view which you seem to imply with
your assumption is inconceivable then
the assumption becomes redundant and it
fades so that punch-up Adamic under
uh-huh far out gets affected by
assumption yep
it's basically fine fine I guess that
you think you are
yeah that's that's why I keep saying
that is the starting point for everyone
people who really think our case so
there is these five aggregates did I
keep taking no puta Gina for him the
threshold is pancha open anaconda that's
the threshold for him v assumed
aggregates so he can't see fabric raised by
so he can't see fabric raised by
themselves because if he starts seeing
that he was not seeing the independence
of them he would start to lose his own
intifada he would stop being a petunia but if he
he would stop being a petunia but if he
thinks he sees them as in oh I'm seeing
the family it's a non-practicing not
attachment to them that's the practice
that leads me to saw the party and what
not he he won't make the effort to
really see them because he thinks he
already sees them so that's what he's
saying is where you start he's ignorant
yeah he's in that assumption yeah so
should be can yes so if you recognize
that you're ignorant it means anything
you think you know you must not take for
granted you that's why you must
investigate you must not leave anything
unturned you must look for the meaning
you must clarify the meaning and so on
that's like the older Buddha was talking
about because otherwise you will assume
things that you think you know and
because of that you won't really get to
know what they are
so continue with the suit sir and they
were questioning him
it's a team because thought to each
other because yet although Preston
question and cross question by those
bhikkhus in this way the big who sati
son of a fisherman still adhered didn't
want to move from his view adhere to
that harmful view and continued to
insist upon it so again he clearly did
not see their views a harmful view when
the view is designated harmful view
that's designated by the one who is
reciting the suit for the audience
saying okay he called the harbour view
but from the point of view of sati
Deepika sati
he clearly thought that's what the
Buddha was teaching so he taught the
other monks they were trying to destroy
any my brother and he thought they were
yeah he thought exactly he no this is
the right view you have the wrong yeah
and so the other book is they went they
couldn't do anything about it so they
went to the Buddha and off told the
Buddha about this and asked for his help
and he so they the Buddha asked for him
to call him Santa cuckoo study so he
could question
so anyway bhikkhus sati comes to the
Buddha and the Buddha asks him sati is
it true that the following harmful view
has arisen in you as I understand the
Dumber taught by the best one it is the
same consciousness that runs and wanders
through the round of rebirths sati
replies exactly so venerable sir that's
exactly how I understand it so the
Buddha asked him what is that
consciousness subtle mm-hmm and he says
it is that which speaks and feels and
experiences here and there the result of
good and bad actions that's actually
quite a quite a contemporary view of
consciousness among many people most
people think that like it's your
consciousness that does all this that
gets the distribution of karma they gets
reborn and so on even it don't even if
they don't necessarily call it the
consciousness you might use a different
one and don't use any words at all but
have you still there
that which speaks and feels and
experiences here now the fact that he
even referred it is that means you
you've assumed it as you as if you can
see it as an object oh it's that which
does all these things failing to see
that that thing that you're designating
is that which does all these things
he's a present thing which means there
is a presence in regard to that thing
which means that's what consciousness is
that presence not what you are
designating it to be
and it said the Buddha replies misguided
man but the in the I think he was a
bit harsher than that in the party it
said isn't he calls
bhiku sati a Morgan parisa which
translates as foolish man oh but idiot
useless useless stupid man yeah an idiot
so it says you stupid man to whom have
you ever known me to teach the Dhamma in
that way you stupid man have I not
stated in many ways consciousness to
dependently arisen since without the
condition there is no origination of
consciousness but you stupid man have
misrepresented us by your wrong grasping
and injured yourself and stored up much
demerit for this will lead to your harm
and suffering for a long time so why is
that just because I mean just because in
modern times you say or just because he
understood that misunderstood that
consciousness is yet the Buddha publicly
in front of the whole assembly keeps
calling that man stupid man an idiot -
useless men a fool because he
misunderstood now because he done
anything wrong by body speech remind so
to speak you know he hasn't like broken
the rules or anything like that he just
misunderstood what the Buddha was
teaching and that's how serious that is
today but it says you know just injure
yourself but like lots of future demerit
so to speak
cuz he's be probably going around saying
that that's what the Buddha's teaching
he was teaching that which he thought
the Buddha's teaching one that's not
what he what the Dhamma is that's all it
takes
not clearly knowing that you know but
basing your you sort of hard to put it
based looks like found in your
understanding by establishing your
understanding upon like lack of clarity
upon something that's just agreeable or
pleasing to you what it makes sense
without really understanding why it
makes sense to what extent he make sense
a how it makes sense and why without
really understanding things they don't
make sense why didn't make sense why are
they wrong why does the right things
right basically without understanding
writers right wrong is wrong which is a
criteria for a certain planet and
everybody knows that see that's the
thing he might it sure you might feel sorry
he might it sure you might feel sorry
for him okay well he only misunderstood
what consciousness is why was the Buddha
so harsh publicly humiliating him could
he go you know every will be accumulated
but yeah that's not he's responsible for
it because he wouldn't have arrived at
it without willfully ignoring the fact
that he already knows that he hasn't
fully penetrated and understood and
freed himself from suffering or
understood wholesome his wholesome and
also than all of those things he
basically through his carelessness
ignored that aspect they would have made
him concerned before he started speaking
about what the Buddha is teaching he
just wouldn't be doing it unless he's
clear Oh certainly if he's doing it he
would make sure that he's not sure he
will make sure to tell people that he's
not sure but then you would why would
you would you you wouldn't be teaching
them so the fact that he was
going around and saying this is what the
Lord teaches coming out of his own lack
of effort to understand yeah
that's why it's so bad that's why he's
so responsible for it although like yang
did today modest terms you think what
was the big deal I mean many people
misunderstand many things yeah exactly
that's how big a deal it is
and the Buddha goes on then the blessed
one addressed the bhikkhus the other
because over there thus because what do
you think has this bhikkhus son T son of
a fisherman
Kim kindled even a spark of wisdom in
the stomach and been in discipline well
because that sitting next thing yeah
sir so it's like public humiliation in
school class
is everyone all the other big who say
how could he venerable sir
no venerable sir when this was said the
bhikkhus sati son of a fisherman said
silent dismayed embarrassed with
shoulders drooping depressed head down
glum without response so he wasn't he
wasn't very happy one could say then
knowing this the Blessed One told him
you stupid man again you will be
recognized by your own harmful view
that's how people remember have all yeah
yeah no sir so while he's sitting it is
a shock question the bhikkhus on this
matter then the best one adjusted
because the speakers do to point out
they're like you know some people might
think like well huh why would do that
yeah of course the bullies right but why
was he so rude because he wasn't because
the Buddha is well not even like even so
deep honor would have that perspective
already let alone another hand you
really know important for money order so
upsetting somebody here and now making
him feel ashamed of his wrong with you
boohoo basically he's gonna be upset but
at least he might shake him to his core
and he'll make the effort and understand
as it often happened when they felt
ashamed and even the is that the the
chanting that's kind of done in the
temples in the morning Oh will I be
ashamed at the end of my life if
questioned by other monks like where is
my understanding buddy
develop its it's a very thing that can
spur you to make the air would rightly
and again the Buddhist perspective was
not just oh I must not upset anyone in
this life no he could see that because
of their wrong view if that big who
doesn't abandon it
not just that he'll remain a boot to
Jeana that he won't become another hand
he's going to end up in some horrible
rebirth because he's been going around
saying misrepresenting the buddha then
resulted in other people also thinking
the buddha was teaching that not what
the real Dhamma is and so on basically
being responsible directly or indirectly
for many people's misunderstandings that
then resulted in their misdeeds and
everything else would be on him and he's
harmful view so the Buddha could see
that unless he abandons it he's gonna
paid the price that really nobody wants
to be paying so what is from that point
of view upsetting him now for a few days
that's nothing in comparison that's what
the Buddha meant when he said like when
he gave that similarly like what if we
ever like a single child and he could
swallow something wouldn't you stick
your arm in his throat and put nothing
out even if you made the child bleed and
hurt it you would cause it would at
least save its life as if in a long run
you would save it by harming it
initially by upsetting it initially but
in a way because been recorded sati
or who knows if he changed his view but
right this whole incident can help
others to see what's clearly it's there
as a teaching example means sati but the
fact that he was able to sit through
that means he did sort of do some good
so the big the Buddhist continues to
question the other beakers and they are
all in agreement with him about sati and
so then he makes it the bottom a
statement about consciousness because
consciousness is reckoned by the
particular condition dependent
upon which it arises when consciousness
arises depend on the eye and forms it is
reckoned as unconsciousness and so if
the site is present you're talking about
the presence of sights sound smell taste
touches are present use only one silent
sound smell taste touches their presence
so the presence of these things is what
consciousness is which means trying to
even even the reasoning consciousness is
a separate entity it's completely
mistaken that's why the right the
correct reasoning is the reasoning that
doesn't disassociate consciousness from
the things that's inseparable from
because I said even when you think the
word consciousness in itself that thing
is present in your mind that you are
conscious of so you have to do is stop
misconceiving the that word that stands
for that which presence of things is
because you can't have pure presence you
can't go below it and see it in front of
you always behind so in that sense yeah
present so this is different in presence
of this but yeah overall you can say
presence is there because there is
something present there is this present
with this this is that's the most basic
definition of what is on powder it gives
us simile just as a fire is reckoned by
the particular condition dependence
which it burns when fire burns dependent
on logs it is reckoned as a love fire if
it burns dependent on sticks its reckon
there's a stick fire lights are present
then its presence of sight it's not the
front well yeah but you can as as the nature
well yeah but you can as as the nature
of the aggregate is if you want discern
it you see doesn't matter what presence
it doesn't matter that what presence as
presence of what is present it doesn't
matter what matters is that there is a
presence there in itself of any kind
so whether inside sound smell taste
touches thoughts does matter presence is
there doesn't matter what feel feeling
is there there's Manowar attached
intention and so that's if you try to understand
and so that's if you try to understand
it from the point of view of the
aggregates when you stop being concerned
even with with that relatively known
particular designation of presence of
sights which is quite a general
designation already it's not a presence
of this particular site on account of
that particular site if it's a site
there is a presence of sites means there
is the I consciousness as the suitors
would call it but even then you can go
even more broadly more peripherally and
that's how I started selling the
aggregates when you say well it doesn't
matter even what sense it doesn't matter
what sense the consciousness sort of is
presence of consciousness is there
presence is there and that's why
consciousness is the last aggregate you
can discern in such men and after you
cover everything else because everything
else appears to some extent means
everything else you are conscious of
everything else is present and when you
define fully clarified everything that
is present then you can understand the
nature of presence without making it a
foreground of a new present object which
is what people do and awareness any
continues to question the because on
this because do you see this has come to
be ah I know that bit it's actually the
pali says amongst you see this is or
this has arisen he doesn't say this has
come to be which applies again
origination approaches that you observe
or something coming into being no monks
do you see this is present or this is
that's actually the part says I remember
a translated a bit long time ago in one
of the essays which one
yeah monk do you see this is oh this is
present it's a very present tense
basically it's not like this has come to
be oh yes I saw this having been before
has come to be now do you see this is
this do you see this monks do you see
this is present you can say that yeah
this do you see this do you see this
monks do you see this I say yes
yeah we see that this is present just
because do you see its origination
occurs with that as nutriment do you see
then it originated with that as fuel hmm
so if it's the site you're talking about
take a site we look at at the same site
and you say do you see that these
mountains around us by present do you
see them yes now would you be able to
see as in would you be able would it be
able to be present for you
if there's nothing there to be present
if there is no I to see if there are no
forms to be seen if the eye doesn't
operate well the eye organ is impaired
if something happens to the forms if any
of those things that are after they are
real control if they were not there
would you be still able to say this is
present would you be able to think about
it as present you wouldn't it's so
rooted in that completely sort of thing
that beneath you underneath you you
can't even conceive it what you can miss
consider or not miss conceive it in
which case you get it rightly
that's the more very eyes of the point
the attitude to the phone and so on
so the matter and Rupa to see so if
there were no necessary condition or
thing to be present how can you in call
there is an experience of a sight but
he's asking the most condensed direct
manner or that's the memory was recorded
either worried the context is do you see
this is present as in without anything
to be present can you talk about
presence without making that presence
into this that is present so they say of
course not there needs to be a necessary
condition for it
a nutriment do you see with the
cessation of that human friend what has
come to be subjective so why are you
looking at these mountains imagine
suddenly whatever you your optical core
gets severed so I don't know snaps
inside for whatever some bacteria ate it
and you just go blind we should be still
good to have experience at that site you
wouldn't yet would you be able to stop
that nutriment from disappearing no
that's the definition of nutriment by
the way that's what they're those
contemplations about nutriment there
they're not in your control they're
independent of you yeah nutriment is
something you would eat or take but you
can only do so because it made itself
available to be eaten or taken mmm in
other words it's not lucid in you and
it's even more profound than that
because as I said yeah you can call it a
nutriment but in this case even your own
eyes are not yours so they are part of
the nutriment part of the neutral
relationship upon which the presence of
sight depends on which your whole
experience of visual objects and things
and desire and lastly repulsion depends
but my eyes are gone but then I used to
remember so you just remember the
absence is present now for you the
absence of things used to be seen but
that is present and if you don't see
presence in regard to that there is a
phenomena you're still the victim of the same ROM
you're still the victim of the same ROM
view so yeah what that's saying is that
even if you lose your eyes you can still
become an hour hand based on your
previous experience if you understand it
correctly right here right now in your
thoughts
so this bhikkhus does doubt arise when
one is uncertain thus as this come to be
is this present he's this present does
down to rise so if you're not sure about
the present experience is this is this
is is this thing whatever that is sight
sound smell taste touch it is this thing
present if you stop questioning then you
start doubting it all if you start
questioning maybe you don't question the
obvious presence of your sight but you
start pushing yeah but is it then that
that form is necessary for the presence
of that form two places do you doubt the
because there's a doubt arise when one
is uncertain us does it does its
presence occur with thatis nutriment
exact so whichever aspect you're not
sure about
that's what doubt arises and see what
the Buddha spoke now that's how you go
beyond the doubt from the most
fundamental principle of party to some
bother with this this is oh with this
present this is present but this in this
with this is present that is present but
not that in as in like in terms of like
a second thing after but more like
second thing that's also there but
presence can be discerned in regard to
that which is present simultaneously
with that presence if you start to think
about present separate from the object
that is present you made that presence
into an object that is present which
means it's not the presence you
misconceiving the consciousness in other
way around if you think you can access
the form and matter in the world there
without it being present for you
beforehand you assume like a direct
relationship with matter and song which
is like inconceivable the only way you
can know matter is because it's
manifested its present that's what we
said the matter finds the footing in your
the matter finds the footing in your
experience through you miss conceiving
its presence basically finds the footing
in
by the pudding in consciousness I think
that's how he put it
finds finds a footing means well you
make it to be that which it isn't you
miss conceive it does it's a find a
foodie finds a footing in consciousness
or parts of footing in either way the
four Great elements the four Maha butas
are below your feet so to speak they're
outside of the scope of your experience
you thinking you can relate to them one
way or the other they find the footing
in your experience because of that
because of your misconceiving and again
Mullaperiyar Sutra talks about
approaching these misconceiving and
danyetta that the fourth element sees as
in the only way for them to exist were
being misconceived so if a person doubts
where the presence is independent of
that which is present or whether it's
not independent or whether it's both but
it's not which one comes first
well is this a cause for it he's not
free from damned if he clearly sees for
himself and this is nothing this is
absolute this is as not abstract as you
can get if it's abstract is only because
people have so much work to do in terms
of undoing the wrong views so that then
this starts to make sense but that's not
the reason to not start doing it so this
is the most direct insight basically but
it super defines the Dhamma the defines
freedom from suffering everything else
with this this is with this present this
is as in the two simultaneous things
exactly you can just say no it's only
things that are present or you can say
no all the things are present in my
consciousness or for my consciousness
either way you all shoot the mark no
there is presence of things as in there
is the consciousness and I inform on the
other side there is consciousness and
even sounds on the other side and all
the senses and all the thoughts in mind
so in other words presence is not the
same as things that are present but
presents without things that the present
is utterly inconceivable even if you're
thinking it in your thoughts seriously
you are misconceiving it by doing so so
this mean I must stop doing it you can't
stop doing it but what you can stop
doing is misconceiving while you're
doing it in other words when you think
about presence you stop carrying the
gratuities assumption that is stands for
that pure consciousness that is
underneath which is just a caller
creatures come from view
is it it continues Vickers is doubt
abandoned in one who sees as it actually
is with proper wisdom thus this has come
to be I say yes because his doubt
abandon one who sees as it actually is
was proper wisdom it's a it's originated
its presence occurs with that as
nutriment hmm yes he is doubt abandoning
one who sees as it actually uses proper
wisdom does with a cessation of that
nutriment but has come to be is subject
to cessation yes so it's basically fully
fully clearing any notion of yourself
being involved there being required
there you see there is an experience of
sight then you see the necessary basis
for that experience to arise to manifest
then you see the dead basis is afternoon
out of your control like inconceivable
it's inconceivable that you could stop
your eye from deteriorating with your
heart from from having a heart attack or
your brain from from ceasing to work or
your lungs from stopping to breathe it's
inconceivable that you have a say over
the form that's out there like can only
be misconceived basically because you
there's no way of accessing it so you
fully understand that you stop basically
even the most gratuitous the subtlest of
assumptions you might have had about the
conceit vanity sense of control
self-centeredness self view all of that
will cease because it just utterly
becomes that becomes then inconceivable
all of your conceiving of self view I am
this is mine this is for me all of those
conceiving x' are based on you miss
conceiving that relationship of that
independence you stop miss conceiving
the relationship everything else that
should be conceiving on top of it
becomes inconceivable that's what the
Buddha could categorically say for
somebody with a right view it is
inconceivable to take any determination
and the determination is suffering
anything yourself for somebody with
right view it's inconceivable to do this
to do this to do this for somebody who
is bouncing sure it is inconceivable to
do this there are things that become
utterly inconceivable right here right
now notice what keep you the same thing
here but he is saying do you see this so
you could do you see do you see the
foreground sure and deuce do you
understand that without the background
foreground is impossible would you
understand it you wouldn't be able to
designate the foreground with unless
there is a very full awareness of it
it's not part of that designation so I'm
not human so if I'm with this this is
yeah without this this cannot be that's
a definition but it's a foreground
background is sure with foreground
background can be correctly discerned so
I'm not I'm not exactly thinking about
consciousness I'm not thinking you know
deception that's where the Buddha
wouldn't even say their consciousness he
asked them this do you see this do you
see a phenomenon and not any kind and
nutrients do you see the phenomenon
arising with the nutriment as in
inseparable from its basis inconceivable
without it being present as well yes we
see that but the one who sees that is he
free from doubt about that of course
he's free from doubt for the one who
sees that would he be able to think oh
but if the nutriment of this phenomenon
disappears phenomena will still remain
no that becomes inconceivable as well
but for most people they don't see the
domain of nutriment
no because most most people would see
things well again it comes from that
original sort of view of kind of
assuming a certain external world to
yourself from which you observe things
happening in
to yourself it doesn't matter there's
this whole observation meditation
techniques following your sensations and
whatnot it's all about witnessing and
looking at things
as if that's how you learn their nature
it's all about foreground and collecting
data about the foreground there is no
discernment of the peripheral with the
nature is without making the peripheral
another foreground but just look to the
foreground that's where you stop looking
all my elbows my knees my breath my
people might notice no bodies their
sight is there sound is there smell
taste touches of it thoughts are there
any pick any and you can start ascending
the principle rightly but in order to
pick any you have to undo all these
views they were kind of pulling you into
therefore down even more whereby it's
about observation and witnessing and
catching the moments of impermanence and
whatnot so now look at this foreground
okay I have the information but the
background so sharpen this this comes
about through so many things which is
not this food there's not here yeah yeah
and all of those things can be the right
nutriment they will make you they will
enable you to sort of stop conceiving
yourself as the owner if they're seen
within there isn't thing not before or
after it not as the linear protests as
one leads to two leads to three but one
within one so that's exactly point take
this just say my experience is a whole
mini sitting in this room on the chair
just holding it so that's it just my
birth take anything and just have it
present as a phenomenon that you just
designated in your foreground that's
enduring there and then through that
endurance or that phenomenon allow your
mind to then think about necessity of
food necessity of abating hard necessity
of a certain degree of health necessity
of freedom from accidents necessity of
freedom from to Southern to large change
of an elements
then you realize oh that's why I'm alive
no because I am NOT because I'm in
control but because the life still
hasn't met basically those nutrients
nutrients are still there then and
they're present that's the whole point
even if you're not necessarily ting all
the time the fact that food that you ate
the you that you you you will be eating
and so on
it's there fueling this body because of
which all of this is present your
nutriment is present through that your
birth is present through that not in the
past right there in the present the fact
that this body is here and I don't mean
that momentarily like you born every
second no your birth was manifested and
we call the manifestation of birth we
call it life so your life is what your
birth is what about so I can discern
life the genuine life yes I am Alive and
you can say that the background to that
is the not this either way yeah that
would be like a like a very very subtle
subtle no present phenomenon not absence
absence of death that's where you
analyze and if you want yeah in order to
arrive at it correctly note that you are
not arriving correct if I don't change
for somebody who wants to try that he
might be it might be more prudent to
start with simpler as in it's still the
same principle it's not like all you
start around no it's the same principle
so I am Alive right here right now what
do you think about it or not but do you
pay attention to it or not your life and
yours because in any second if I also
yes of course I'm alive your life is
still there enduring as the utmost
general thing it's even more general
than your particular feelings and moods
they might arise and last for days and
so on
so I am Alive while you are mindful of
that and by my I mean like think I'm
alive and then allow it to go into that
background as in stop trying to actively
repeaters I'm alive I'm alive I'm alive let it
I'm alive I'm alive I'm alive let it
drift away so to speak without
completely forgetting about it I'm alive
because I'm alive I can talk here
because I'm alive I'm sitting here I
will go hungry later I will do this
later because I'm alive I can read the
sutras because I'm alive I can practice
them that's one direction now you can
take that further and or the opposite
way and say I am Alive because them is
the beating heart in me I am Alive
because my mother raised me my mother
fed me where I could when I couldn't I
am Alive because there is still food -
edible present for me as an option I am
Alive because the five aggregates are
still not destroyed that's it but you
need to like anybody can see that and
anybody can say that but it's very hard
to do it properly and by properly I mean
see this party to some Father
that's why we're now under said to the
Buddha oh this embodies so obvious of
course you see it in everything because
it's the principle of simultaneous
presence of this because of this but if
you said oh don't say that it's actually
very very subtle thing to see now of
course you've been looking at it for
twenty years that's all you see but most
people because they don't see that
obvious thing in a way they don't see it
correctly they remain bound to samsara
and correctly means seeing that
relationship with dependence not just
manufacturing it based on your idea but
it's own father
so while say to yourself I am Alive
right here right now I am still alive
and still it's enduring my life is
enduring I don't have to make any
efforts like directly to keep Michalak
know you're alive
now why am i alive while I'm alive so
why in my life while I am Alive which
means you still mind for the you are
alive but you start looking for why
within that mindfulness so why because
there is this heart still beating and if
that thing stops I cannot conceive life
anymore no matter how much I might resist it if
no matter how much I might resist it if
my pathways always get sort of
obstructed my legs collapse undone and
that is inconceivable to prevent
if it were to happen yet I'm alive
right here right now he's fully
dependent upon it fully determined by
there is its core nutrient presence of
operating organs organs that are on the
level of chair table everything else but
if you just see them as a chair table
and everything else you're not seeing
that mutant relationship that's why the
Buddha never said oh yeah look at this
this stone is free from self and it's
impermanent and you or no because you're
indifferent over the stone fine things
you're not indifferent about and within
them discern their dependence on a
certain nutriment such as present body
and living body
freedom from accident all of these
things that's what the Buddha asked them
the macsyna to taint the forest he said
monks would you be upset if like like
people come in this woodland where we
are sitting now and start collecting all
these twigs and branches and breaking
even burning them you know of course we
wouldn't be upset why because like those
branches and allows we don't care about
that and he said so you should develop
the same attitude towards your own body
towards your own senses as in you need
to see that it can't be yours even if
you want to be yours and you see that
the cameos were recognizing the
relationship of nutriment the definition
of but it some bother with this this is
if the reasonable operating organs or
rock-hard whichever we were single out
or one doesn't matter if there is no
body being alive there for which we have
no say you couldn't be present right
here right now experience in these
things but that recognition must not be
seen as before or after or one moment
before the next moment no must be seen
within the enduring peripheral awareness
of the fact that you are alive while you
are thinking that hence yo Mistah
monastic are we spoke about before and
again in a way it's like all people
would have to do in order to see it is
stop trying to catch it stop trying to
see momentarily that's what they often talk
momentarily that's what they often talk
about the time as in people assuming
linearly and that's how you exclude
yourself out what you need to do is just
a lot of things to be stopped trying to
do it let's see the project but not like
or just be no you need to discern
something within that just be because my
phone is in itself well it's not like
fulness only mindfulness that's
understood based on the principle
mindfulness is can be called the right
mindfulness so that's what I mean when
we spoke about before about the mood two
different things allow it to induce so
yeah as you would have said monks do you
see this is that this did the Buddha
refers to can be pretty much any general
thing you want to attend to so just say
to yourself I am alive and don't try to
force it or try to keep you are still
alive even even if you start doubting it
yeah but didn't I just say that
everything is because you're already
alive and that's already can be
discerned in the peripheral of whatever
you're attending so one that once that
comes down then within that peripheral
if I'm alive because there is a beating
heart within this I'm alive I'm alive
because the senses are still operating
within this I'm alive because the
nutriment is still available of food I'm
alive because that the random
consciousness hasn't turned away from an
object as the Buddha would say from nama
Rupa I'm alive because I'm not dead yeah
I'm alive because death hasn't affected
me yet but see the fact that death can
affect that because of which you are
alive means you you have no say in
either life know that whatever you do is
secondary to it secondary is in not
after in a sense of time but secondary
it's sort of after within it as an
insect it's not as fundamental
so yes you're the only reason you're
alive is because you're not dead and
that's why modern under sati is like the
quickest in the sharpest way to free
yourself from any dis passion and lust
and become an ardent the presence of the
absence of death sure is the nutrient
film well it's the it's the condition
for your life
it determines your life because if the
absence of death becomes sorry if the
absence of death ceases to be absent
your life come and see you can discern
that as on that level of possibility as
in you can discern it peripherally is a
possibility but it's a you cannot
possibly approach it or do anything
about it which means it's certainty
possibilities are certain they're
possible in the content but certain in
the nature and that usually problem good
people would dismiss possibilities as if
not applicable to me usually because of
the relative content it could be this or
it can be that the fact is it will be
one way or the other and that's what
another another cryptic passage it will
it will not be and it will not be for me
means you stop being concerned with the
content of what it will be but you
discerned it whatever it will be it
won't be for me as in I'm redundant
either way even in the utmost remote
uncertainty of the content of the utmost
remote possibilities you are redundant
and that's what you discern and that's
no no amount of content which can affect
you or reduce the sense of self in
conceiving in appropriation I'm trying
to get to this point of Nirvana I'm
trying to where Disney benefit you and
now you've brought that up listed one of
the practices sure sure oh sure
discerning opponent so exciting we spoke
about before and we got to yeah
discerning Aparna well you would descend
abandoners if the the absence
sorry the presence of the absence of
your death
is my present because action this death
is an absent death is absent in his
particular manifestation but it's very
present in its nature that's what it
would have said if you practice
mindfulness of death correctly it's like
why are you breathing in your thinking I
might not live long to breathe out cuz
that's how present death is and I will
not yeah sure if you happened you will
not but usually people are will die in
20-30 years then there amongst will
bring it closer well you know am I not
finished by the next morning I might not
wake up then the one I might die before
I finish this meal then there is one I
might die before I take the next breath
and then the one said I might die when I
inhale before I exhale and the Buddha
said you are the only one betting it
correctly because that's how present
that possibility of death is but because
people don't see it they only look at
the particular as particular pose isn't
the particular aspect of that
possibility and by particular last week
I mean the possible particular
manifestation of it failing to see that
doesn't matter the manifestation the
possibility is certain the nature it is
certain so death is certain I mean if
you understand that that's when the
banner is because there is a complete
dispatch of this passion that sergeant
Chapman died before you died fully fully
understand develop your mind in regard
to death before it actually comes in a
particular manner and swipes the way
your body that's what the ban is that's
what petitioners will be terrified of me
bana whenever they heard the Buddha
described it or they will kill me
because they would still be coming from
the sense of self an assumed external
point of view that it's in charge of
everything master of everything
controller of everything owner of
everything yet this comes right from
your very center of your being from your
heart so it's very frightening because
because death I mean I'm not dying not
death and this is because the end is not said
and this is because the end is not said
it again this is because the end you is
absent right the the particular
manifestation of that death but the end
the complete cessation complete
cessation oh I see what you mean right
yeah that's what that not that's what
death isn't for a bit Aegina in other
words if petitioner dies it's not a
complete cessation yeah death is another
experience a complete cessation would be
utter hunt and party nirvana and that
can't be present no well it's present
for another for another hunt party
Nirvana is present that's why there's no
problem enduring difficult
sorry pardon Ivana by developing the
bona party bonding present when the
residue of the body breaks up a complete
cessation that is the complete cessation
yeah and even trying to conceive else
after is inconceivable but yet people
think again with the assumption of a
still of you how we started this whole
thing with that suta people assume the
contents of your life reason like you
know eventually to death and then the
new content start if you believe any but
it not doesn't matter you still assume
that linear progression but death is an
experience in itself that has a reason
and you've no idea only lost because you
never experienced it so the Assumption
the death it just is about ending of
these particular things it's completely
true this as well
but the assumption that death is the new
beginning it's equally Jesus he's no
idea what that is but thinking that he
lost momentarily he's rather foolish
because the Buddha himself said pains of
death or those of dying
whenever he want to illustrate you can
be the great pains and you mean they say
all that sort of manner can become
another at the moment of the death
there's no moment there's the experience
of death and that experience can last
for a long time so yeah somebody with
the right view who have plenty of time
to become
and there and then because there is
nothing coming through his senses
distracting him anymore that's what they
said Souter but it says sotapanna if he
doesn't become our in this life he
becomes another hunt when he upon dying
or if he doesn't be coming out in this
life or when he dies he becomes another
but he's like you remember basically in
between you doing during the dying
whatever oh if he doesn't come around
then he becomes a nun upon landing as
close as you can hang that translation
but he's not upon landing then upon the
next life and so on in other words
people need to stop thinking these
momentary successions of experiences is
what my experience is because that's a
completely gratuitous external point of
view either you go after yourself you
yourself cannot see yourself like that
you can only assume and then act out of
that assumption which actually
contributes you're very experienced
hence it's a wrong harmful view our
continued is almost finished this
questions its ability computed continues
his biggest are you thus free from doubt
here this has come to me yes venerable
sir this is risen because are you thus
free from data its origination occurs
with thatis nutriment yes Mendelssohn
its presence is because it's nutrient is
present and Biggers are you thus free
from doubt here with a cessation of that
nutriment what has come to be you see
the absence of nutriment goes sorry if
the if the nutriment is absent came to
think that's present because of the
nutriment stay present absolutely not
even for a second longer beyond death
with this this is without this this
isn't that's it but it's no bother
and because has it been seen well by you
as it actually is with proper wisdom
thus this has come to be and I will say
yes van booster has it been seen has it
been seen well by you as it actually is
a proper wisdom to origination occurs
without his nutriment yes and he goes on
for the big who's purified and bright as
this view is if you adhere to it
cherish it treasure it and treated as a
possession would you then understand
the Dumber has been taught as similar to
a raft being for the purpose of crossing
over not for the purpose of grasping so
no Venables sir
bigger is purified and bright as this
view is if you do not adhere to a
treasure it cherish it and treated as
possession would you then understand
that the Dhamma has been taught as
similar to a raft being full of purpose
of crossing over not for the purpose of
grasping yes Vanessa so if you don't
cherish the right of you yeah means they
were old at least saw the banners for
even more he doesn't necessarily specify
because those specifications came later
it's about seeing the dam or not seeing
the Dhamma he's not in between mm-hmm so
they'll see the Dhamma they all have the
clear view but some of them might not be
exposing that you as it might not be
dwelling on it and not be drilling it
because it's such an amazing view it's
such an insight that they might already
be happy with it but it wouldn't say and
then you can't protect it in a way
automatically simply by not not trying
to dismantle everything the needs to be
dismantled that's what he would urge
people who've seen the Dhamma who've
seen the nature Nibbana to make the
effort further in that sense know just
what you got don't just cherish it then
they put it on a shelf use it use it and
use it and use it because it will only
get stronger and then you go beyond it
don't be lazy don't be distracted
and the risks that the suitor continues
a little bit about nutriment and then
goes into 50 to some part on a more
particular explanation or descriptions
yeah of course because it's all about
petition father and say they would birth
as a condition
whichever phenomenon you take generally
you can discern its nutriment within it
and that's exactly why petite simpler
starts in such a broad manner not always
for n sorry in a broad manner but not
always something the Buddha would define
it differently with no 12 factors but 16
rate factors
these vicars remember this discourse of
mind briefly as the deliverance in the
destruction of craving but remember the
big who sati son of a fisherman has
caught up in a vast net of craving in a
trammel of craving yeah but is a lot
more to the suitor